Inventory of the Ethelbert Talbot Papers, 1848-1961 (bulk 1869-1928)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Ethelbert Talbot papers
1848-1961 (bulk 1869-1928)
Talbot, Ethelbert
02418
3.50 cubic ft. (8 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Diaries and other personal papers of an Episcopalian missionary bishop of Wyoming and Idaho (1887-1897) and bishop of Central Pennsylvania (1898-1928).
Biography of Ethelbert Talbot
Ethelbert Talbot (1848-1928) was born in Missouri. He graduated from Dartmouth College and the General Theological Seminary of the Episcopal Church and began his clerical career as rector of the Episcopal Church in Macon, Missouri, in 1873. In 1887 he was elected missionary bishop of Wyoming and Idaho, an office which required him to travel great distances through thinly-populated country often under difficult conditions. There were at that time only four Episcopal clergymen at work in Wyoming and only six church buildings. Bishop Talbot chose Laramie, Wyoming, as his see city, and he oversaw the building of St. Matthew's cathedral there between 1892 and 1897. In 1898 he was chosen bishop of Central Pennsylvania and went to live in Bethlehem, Pennsylvania. In 1924, he became Presiding Bishop of the Church. Ethelbert Talbot married Dora Harvey (1850-1920), and they were the parents of one daughter, Anne Harvey Talbot (Donaldson) (b. 1875).
Scope and Content
The Ethelbert Talbot Papers consist primarily of the personal papers and diaries of Ethelbert Talbot. The diaries record daily activities and the correspondence is, for the most part, private letters from Talbot to his wife and daughter. There are also occasional letters from other family members and a few from Talbot's colleagues regarding church business. There is some correspondence regarding publication of Talbot’s autobiographical books; and there are some short manuscripts and sermons written by Talbot and others. Church records, although not entirely absent, are scattered and incomplete. There are three scrapbooks containing clippings, printed material, and some hand-written documents regarding Ethelbert Talbot, the Talbot family, and various friends and colleagues. Clippings and miscellaneous documents were also found tucked into the diary pockets, and this material had been retained with the diaries. There are also four photograph albums and some loose photographs.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Ethelbert Talbot at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
The bulk of the Ethelbert Talbot papers were given to the American Heritage Center by Francis Donaldson between 1967 and 1970. A few items were also received from Anne Talbot Donaldson in 1963 and Mable Brown in 1966.
Access Terms
Donaldson, Anne Talbot -- Diary.; Episcopal Church -- (Wyoming); Episcopal Church -- (Idaho); Episcopal Church -- (Pennsylvania); St. Matthew's Cathedral (Laramie, Wyo.); Parish missions -- Anglican Communion -- Wyoming.; Parish missions -- Anglican Communion -- Idaho; Parish missions -- Anglican Communion -- Pennsylvania; Frontier and pioneer life -- West (U.S.); Cathedrals -- Wyoming; Laramie (Wyo.); Wyoming -- History -- To 1889; Wyoming -- History -- 1890-1918; Wyoming -- History -- 1919-1945; Diaries; Photographs
Immigration and American Expansion; Missionaries; Pioneers; Social Life and Customs; Religion; Wyoming; Diaries
Container List
- Personal Information and Church Records, 1848-ca. 1934; Series I.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title. Contains sermons and writings by Talbot and others, district and general convocation programs, a small number of church records, and biographical and genealogical information.
  - Biographical -- Ethelbert Talbot, 1898-circa 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical -- Ethelbert Talbot -- Obituaries and Memorials, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical and Genealogical -- Talbot Family, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Church Records -- Lists of Churches and Members -- Wyoming and Idaho (incomplete and damaged from use as a scrapbook), 1896-1897, 1902, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Church Records -- Newcastle, Wyoming, deeds (photocopies), 1890, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Church Records -- Pennsylvania and Miscellaneous, 1848-circa 1879, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Convention Programs (Missionary districts and Bishops’ general), 1881, 1885, 1895, 1898, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sermons by Talbot, 1888-circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sermons by Others, 1910, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Writings -- In Wyoming and Idaho (preface), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Writings -- Old Chief Washakie, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Writings -- Some Account…of the Wyoming and Idaho Mission, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Writings -- The Tenderfoot and Old Pete, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Diaries, 1869-1928; Series II.
  - Ethelbert Talbot, 1869-1928; Subseries I.
    Arranged chronologically. Journals of Talbot’s daily activities; also includes some news clippings and miscellaneous inserts.
    - Diary and Lecture Notes (bound out of order), 1869-1876 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - General Theological Seminary, 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Missouri, 1882-1884 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Missouri and Western Tour, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Wyoming, 1888-1893, 1895-1896 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
    - Pennsylvania, 1899-1900 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Pennsylvania, 1901-1912 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
    - Pennsylvania, 1913-1914, 1916-1925 (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
    - Pennsylvania, 1926-1928 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Annie Talbot, 1892-1893; Subseries II.
    Arranged chronologically. Journals of Annie Talbot’s travels in Europe.
    - Shipboard, Germany, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Italy, France, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1869-1961; Series III.
  Arranged chronologically. Primarily private letters from Ethelbert Talbot to his wife and daughter; includes a small amount of church-related and other business correspondence.
  - Dartmouth and Seminary, 1869-1872 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Macon, Missouri, 1873-1882 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Wyoming, 1887 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Idaho, 1887 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Wyoming, 1888-1889 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Boise, Laramie, New York and East Coast, 1890-1891 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - New York, Ohio, Wyoming, Idaho, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - New Jersey, England, Washington, Laramie, New York, Philadelphia, 1894-1895 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Wyoming, New York, at sea, England, May-July, 1897 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - England, Idaho, Washington, August-Nov., 1897 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Pennsylvania and East Coast, 1899-1900, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Harper & Brothers, Publishers, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Church Business, 1919-1928 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Regarding Ethelbert Talbot, 1955, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Photographs, 1895-1919; Series IV.
  Arranged roughly chronologically. Includes albums of Laramie and of Wyoming ranches and camping trips kept by Annie H. Talbot. Also includes loose prints from scrapbooks and diaries.
  - Album -- Laramie, Wyoming, and vicinity, 1895-1896 (Box 6)
  - Album -- of Annie H. Talbot: Wyoming and Idaho; South Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, June-Sept., 1898 (Box 6)
  - Album -- of Annie H. Talbot: Indians and ranch life, 1902 (Box 6)
  - Album -- Rev. Sherman Coolidge; camping, 1902-1903 (Box 6)
  - Portraits of Ethelbert Talbot; tintypes of children, circa 1890s-circa 1920s (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Loose prints from 1911-1919 scrapbook: Ethelbert Talbot and others, 1914, 1920, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Scrapbooks, 1887-1920; Series V.
  Arranged roughly chronologically. Primarily news clippings and printed material regarding Ethelbert Talbot. Includes some primary documents on church business.
  - Loose material from various scrapbooks -- Wyoming, Idaho, 1887-1898 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Reviews of My People of the Plains, etc., 1906-1907 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Church Matters, Talbot Family -- clippings, photographs, correspondence, 1911-1919 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Ethelbert Talbot -- loose material from 1911-1919 scrapbook, circa 1911-1923 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Talbot Family -- loose material from 1911-1919 scrapbook, circa 1911-1923 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Poetry -- loose material from 1911-1919 scrapbook, circa 1911-circa 1923 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Primary Material -- loose material from 1911-1919 scrapbook, 1894-1921, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous -- loose material from 1911-1919 scrapbook, 1891-1924, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Lambeth Conference, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Lambeth Conference -- loose material, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Oversize, circa 1870-1926; Series VI.
  Certificates, maps, printed material.
  - Certificates -- Dartmouth, ca. 1870, 1887 (Box 8)
  - Certificate -- Diocese of Central Pennsylvania, ca. 1905 (Box 8)
  - Certificate -- Lehigh University, 1926 (Box 8)
  - Magazine -- Harper’s Weekly: Henry Mills Alden’s 70th Birthday, part 2, Dec. 15, 1906 (Box 8)
  - Map -- Diocese of Bethlehem (Pennsylvania), 1919 (Box 8)